Guide to the Eugenia Flatow Papers 1940-2011 (bulk 1963-2005) MS 3175
New-York Historical Society
Eugenia Flatow papers
1940-2011 (bulk 1963-2005)
New-York Historical Society
Flatow, Eugenia M., 1921–2015
MS 3175
40 Linear feet in 40 record cartons and 4 oversize folders.
610 Megabytes (449 digital files)
Files documenting the career of Eugenia Flatow (1921–2015), who served as executive secretary of New York City's Model Cities program from 1966 to 1970. Later records chronicle her roles in several civic and environmental organizations dedicated to improving conditions in New York City, with a particular focus on housing and urban development, environmental policy, coastal management, and waterfront revitalization.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in the following series:
Series I. Model Cities, 1958-1984 (bulk 1963-1973)
Series II. Housing and Urban Development, 1948-2011 (bulk 1970s-1980s)
Series III. Waterfronts, Waterways, and Waterborne Transportation, 1943-2005 (bulk 1970s-1990s)
Series IV. Organizational Records, 1961-2010 (bulk 1970s-1990s)
Series V. Personal Files, 1940-2007
Series VI. Photographs and Digital Media, 1990s-2000s
Conditions Governing Access
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit. Researchers will be restricted to view-only settings when requesting remote access to digital materials.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Dr. Evan Flatow in 2021 and 2022.
Biographical / Historical
Eugenia Mortlock Flatow (1921 – 2015), also known as "Genie," was an industrial engineer, management consultant, and citizen advocate dedicated to improving the living conditions in New York City, with a focus on neighborhood revitalization, waterfront development, and environmental issues. She graduated A.B. cum laude from the College of New Rochelle and earned an M.S. in Industrial Engineering from Columbia University. Flatow was active in local politics and ran for city council in 1965 on a platform with three cornerstones: political independence, management reorganization, and improved city services. She did not win, but her progressive political interests shed light on the work she would carry out for the next 50 years.
In the 1960s, Eugenia Flatow served for five years in New York Mayor John Lindsay's Cabinet as Acting Coordinator of Housing and Development, Administrator of Model Cities, and consultant to the Chairman of City Planning. As part of President Lyndon Johnson's War on Poverty, the goal of the Model Cities program was to improve the social, physical, and economic conditions of the poorest neighborhoods in the United States. In her role as Administrator for Model Cities (1966-1970), Flatow advocated scatter-site, vest-pocket public housing, and mandated locally sponsored community revitalization. In the 1980s, Flatow served for four years as Executive Deputy Secretary of State under NY Secretary of State Basil Paterson, during which she was responsible for strategic state planning, coastal management, weatherization, and community development.
Throughout the course of her career, Eugenia Flatow held several leadership positions in numerous civic and environmental organizations dedicated to parks and open space development, environmental policy, and waterfront revitalization. She was a Trustee of The City Club of New York and Chair of its Environmental Committee; President of The Parks Council; Chair of the NYC Soil & Water Conservation District Board; Treasurer of Friends of Gateway and the Neighborhood Open Space Coalition; member of the Management Committee and Co-chair of the Citizens Advisory Committee of the NY/NJ Harbor Estuary Program; Chair of Manhattan Community Board #9's Public Services Committee; Coordinator of the Coalition for the Bight; and Vice President of the Environmental Policy Forum.
Flatow is often referred to as a trailblazer for her success in both raising a family and maintaining a decades-long political career in a male-dominated field. Her governmental and public service has left a lasting impact, and many praise her for her contributions to the environment and New York City as a whole. After her passing, her son, Evan Flatow, stated in an interview that Flatow was a "champion of New Yorkers." Her lifelong commitment to ensuring that the voices of New Yorkers were heard demonstrates this, starting with the community participation aspect of Model Cities and ending with the various calls for community input as part of her work later in her career.
Scope and Contents
The Eugenia Flatow papers consist of correspondence, printed materials, published and unpublished reports, subject files, photographs, digital media, and oversized material that document Flatow's decades-long career in civil service.
Approximately half of the collection includes records from her time as Administrator of the Model Cities program under the John Lindsay administration from 1966 to 1970. These records present the entire application process for Model Cities funding and the housing and urban development projects that were part of the program. There is also extensive documentation that provides a preliminary view of the problems, objectives, and approaches in the Model Cities neighborhoods (Central Brooklyn, South Bronx, and Harlem – East Harlem).
In addition to the Model Cities material, there are records of Flatow's work in housing and urban development after the program ended in the mid-1970s. The files from this work document her consultancy work on numerous housing projects and demonstrate her interests in mutual housing, infrastructure reliability, affordable housing, and equitable housing policy. As her career progressed, Flatow became increasingly involved in the areas of waterfront development and revitalization, coastal management, the quality of New York City's water supply, and environmental policy.
The collection also holds the records of nine different civic and environmental organizations and task forces in which Eugenia Flatow served a prominent role. The materials for each organization are not comprehensive, but the correspondence, minutes, agendas, financial records, and other materials in the collection document the inner workings of these organizations from the perspective of Flatow's role in them.
Few materials in this collection document Eugenia Flatow's personal life, most of which only cover her undergraduate and graduate school years. There is, however, material from her campaign for councilman-at-large that reveals aspects of her early career, political ideology, and family life as of the early to mid-1960s.
The materials arrived in boxes that were organized and labeled according to their contents. It is unclear who performed this arrangement, but this order is reflected in the arrangement and description of the collection. Many folders in this collection were labeled by Eugenia Flatow, and all original file names have been preserved. Folders in poor condition were discarded, but many were retained. A sizable amount of material arrived in hanging files, which were removed for storage and preservation purposes. There were also several binders of material included in the collection; in most instances, documents were removed for preservation purposes and the binders.
There are 10 CDs included in the collection that contain digital versions of photographs taken at events planned by the New York City Soil and Water Conservation District (NYCSWCD). Many of these files are duplicates of photos found elsewhere in the collection, but they offer insight into the events (most notably educational programming for New York City school children) that Flatow attended or helped organize.
City planning -- New York (State) -- New York.; Coastal zone management.; Environmental policy.; Environmentalism.; Housing -- New York (State) -- New York.; Housing development.; Open spaces.; Urban renewal -- Citizen participation.; Waterfronts -- New Jersey.; Waterfronts -- New York (State) -- New York.; Women and city planning -- New York (State) -- New York.; Articles; Administrative records.; Brochures.; Charts; Digital file formats.; Drafts; Financial records.; Letters (correspondence); Maps.; Memorandums.; Organization files.; Pamphlets.; Photographs.; Bronx (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Harlem (New York, N.Y.); Jamaica Bay (N.Y.); Queens (New York, N.Y.); Manhattan (New York, N.Y.); New York Harbor (N.Y. and N.J.).; New York (N.Y.). Department of Environmental Protection; New York (N.Y.). Department of City Planning.; New York (N.Y.). Department of Ports and Terminals; New York Urban Coalition (N.Y.); United States. Department of Housing and Urban Development
- Series I. Model Cities, 1958-1984 (bulk 1963-1973)
  Biographical / Historical
  The Model Cities Program was a component of President Lyndon Johnson's War on Poverty. It was authorized by the Demonstration Cities and Metropolitan Development Act of 1966 and administered by the United States Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD). The program was designed to help selected cities all over the United States improve the social, physical, and economic conditions of poor neighborhoods. The law required and emphasized the need for widespread citizen participation, which gave citizens of model neighborhoods direct access to decision-making to influence the planning and carrying out of the program. In New York City, the program focused on three main areas: Central Brooklyn, South Bronx, and Harlem – East Harlem. The program ended nationally in 1974.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I contains correspondence, evaluations, minutes, proposals, phone messages, population data, reading files, reports, and other documentation related to Eugenia Flatow's role as executive director of the New York Model Cities program. The bulk of these records document the application process for Model Cities funding, which involved an analysis of the model neighborhood's problems, their causes, and the interrelationship of those causes.
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized in five subseries:
  Subseries I.A. Program Development, 1959-1978 (bulk 1968-1973)
  Subseries I.B. Needs Analysis, 1968-1969
  Subseries I.C. Phone Messages, 1966, 1968-1970
  Subseries I.D. Reading Files, 1966, 1968-1969
  Subseries I.E. Subject Files, 1958-1984 (bulk 1965-1973)
  - Subseries I.A. Program Development, 1959-1978 (bulk 1968-1973)
    Subseries I.A. includes correspondence, reports, budgets, administrative records, fact sheets, proposals, draft applications, and introductory information related to the development of the Model Cities program in New York City, as well as initial plans for activity in Central Brooklyn, South Bronx, and Harlem – East Harlem.
    Materials in this subseries are arranged chronologically.
    - Preliminary Plan, West Side Urban Renewal, 1959 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    - Urban Renewal Flowcharts (1 of 2), 1965 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
      2 items moved to an oversize container.
    - Urban Renewal Flowcharts (2 of 2). Oversize, 1965 (Folder OS-Large, Folder 2)
      File contains a Flowchart of Urban Renewal Operations and a Project Activity Time Schedule from the Bureau of Project Development, Housing and Redevelopment Board.
    - An Analysis of Current City-Wide Housing Need, 1965 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    - Housing and Urban Renewal Task Force (3 Folders), 1965-1967 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4-6)
    - Housing Reports, 1965-1968 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
    - Housing Reorganization, 1966 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
    - Materials on Reorganization, 1966 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
    - Relocation Manual for Urban Renewal, 1966 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
    - The World of 207, 1966 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    - Draft Model Cities Application, 1966 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
    - Model Cities Introduction, 1966 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
    - Improving the Quality of Urban Life, 1966-1967 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
    - New York City Housing Authority Project Statistics, 1966-1967 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
    - Housing Statistics Handbooks, 1966-1968 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
    - Fact Sheets, 1966-1968 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
    - Model Cities Booklets, 1966-1969 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18)
    - Model Cities Program Draft Summary of Proposal, 1967 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
    - City Planning Maps (1 of 2), 1967 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 20)
      7 items moved to an oversize container.
    - City Planning Maps (2 of 2). Oversize, 1967 (Folder OS-Large, Folder 3)
      File contains 5 zoning maps of Bedford-Stuyvesant, Mott Haven, Milbank-Frawley, Twin Parks, and East New York from the City of New York Housing and Development Administration. There is also a map from a Bedford-Stuyvesant Renewal and Rehabilitation Study and an Area Services Project.
    - Plans for Mott Haven, Bedford-Stuyvesant, and East New York, 1967 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 21)
    - HUD Brochures, 1967 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22)
    - Establishment of The Model Cities Committee, 1967-1968 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
    - Proposed Work Program, 1967-1968 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
    - HUD Handbooks, 1967-1969 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
    - Directories, 1968 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
    - Basic Data: Model Cities Program Areas, 1968 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
    - Model Cities Programs (2 Folders), 1968 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6-7)
      This file contains descriptions and data for several Model Cities programs. Program areas include: economic development, education, higher education, environmental protection, health care, public safety, recreation and culture, human resources, and housing and urban development.
    - Model Cities: A Bibliography, 1968 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
    - Preliminary Draft - Working Document, 1968 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
    - Bi-Monthly Planning Progress Report, 1968 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 10)
    - East New York Open Space Study, 1968 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 11)
    - Renewal Planning and Management System Draft Proposals, 1968 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12)
    - Strategies for Shaping Model Cities, 1968 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 13)
    - Model Cities Social Planning Kit, 1968 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 14)
    - Glossary of Model Cities Related Terms and Concepts, 1969 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 15)
    - Budget Request (1970-1971), 1969 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 16)
    - Election Procedures for Model Cities, 1969 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 17)
    - The Citizen - Planner Speaks, 1969 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 18)
    - Participation in Model Cities Planning, 1969 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 19)
    - New York City Model Cities Proposal Evaluation Volume I and II, 1969 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 20)
    - New York Model Cities Program Introduction [disassembled binder] (3 Folders), 1969-1970 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1-3)
    - 1968 Central Brooklyn Model Cities Household Survey, 1970 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 4)
    - Program for the Expansion of Day Care Services, 1970 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 5)
    - Model Cities Administration: Second Quarterly Report (4 Folders), 1970 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 19-22)
    - Model Cities Administration: Third Quarterly Report, 1970 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 6)
    - Model Cities Administration: Fourth Quarterly Report, 1970 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 7)
    - Model Cities Administration: Fifth Quarterly Report, 1970 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 8)
    - Model Cities Administration: Tenth Quarterly Report, 1971 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 9)
    - Madison Mall, 1971 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 10)
    - Proposed Training Program: Uniformed Services Trainee, 1971 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 11)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1968-1972 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 12)
    - Model Cities Monthly Bulletin, 1969-1971 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 13)
    - Other Model Cities Programs, 1969-1972 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 14)
    - Report on NYC Model Cities, 1973 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 15)
    - Large-Scale Development in New York City, 1973 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 16)
    - Central Brooklyn Model Cities Master Development Plan, 1973 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 17)
    - 1978 Annual Report (Offsite-box 5, Folder 18)
  - Subseries I.B. Needs Analysis, 1968-1969
    To receive Model Cities funding, cities were required to file a report with the United States Department of Housing and Urban Development on the problems, goals, and strategies of their Model Cities program. Subseries I.B. consists of studies, data, and draft proposals related to this part of the application process. The documents provide a preliminary view of the problems, objectives, and approaches in Central Brooklyn, Harlem – East Harlem, and South Bronx.
    - Problem Analysis, Overview and Education [disassembled binder] (3 Folders), 1968 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1-3)
    - Problem Analysis, Neighborhood Sanitation & Safety and Economic Support & Development [disassembled binder] (3 Folders), 1968 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 4-6)
    - Problem Analysis, Health & Multiservice Systems and Neighborhood Development [disassembled binder] (3 Folders), 1968 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 7-9)
    - Needs Analysis [disassembled binder] (3 Folders), 1968 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 10-12)
      Binder consists of raw data for the citywide and model cities needs analysis.
    - Problem Analysis, Overview (draft), 1968 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 13)
    - Problem Analysis, Education (draft), 1968 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 14)
    - Problem Analysis, Neighborhood Sanitation & Safety (draft), 1968 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 15)
    - Problem Analysis, Economic Support & Development (draft), 1968 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 16)
    - Problem Analysis, Health & Multiservice Systems (draft), 1968 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 17)
    - Problem Analysis, Neighborhood Development (draft), 1968 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 18)
    - The Need, 1969 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
      An analysis of the needs and quality of services in Central Brooklyn.
    - Central Brooklyn Model Cities, Vol. 1: Introduction (2 Folders), 1969 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 2-3)
    - Central Brooklyn Model Cities, Vol. 2: Physical Development, 1969 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 4)
    - Central Brooklyn Model Cities, Vol. 3: Education, 1969 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 5)
    - Central Brooklyn Model Cities, Vol. 4: Economic Development, 1969 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 6)
    - Central Brooklyn Model Cities, Vol. 5: Sanitation and Safety, 1969 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 7)
    - Central Brooklyn Model Cities, Vol. 6: Multi-Services, 1969 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 8)
    - Appendix [2 disassembled binders] (2 Folders), 1969 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 9-10)
      This document is an appendix to the Central Brooklyn Model Cities needs analysis. It contains population data from Central Brooklyn, correspondence, charts, notes, budgetary information, and other documentation related to the Central Brooklyn Model Cities plan.
  - Subseries I.C. Phone Messages, 1966, 1968-1970
    Subseries I.C contains typed summaries of phone messages left for Mrs. Flatow from 1966, 1968-1970. Topics include scheduling meetings, issues within the model neighborhoods, and other Model Cities-related matters.
    Materials in this subseries are arranged in the order they arrived in.
    - Phone Messages, 1966 April-October (Offsite-box 6, Folder 1-6)
    - Phone Messages, 1968 January-June (Offsite-box 6, Folder 7-12)
    - Phone Messages, 1968 July-December (Offsite-box 6, Folder 13-18)
    - Phone Messages, 1969 January-June (Offsite-box 6, Folder 19-24)
    - Phone Messages, 1969 July-1970 January (Offsite-box 6, Folder 25-26)
    - Phone Messages, 1969 July-1970 January (Offsite-box 7, Folder 1-5)
  - Subseries I.D. Reading Files, 1966, 1968-1969
    Subseries I.D. contains Model Cities-related correspondence that was circulated in Mrs. Flatow's office for reading and/or reference.
    - Reading Files, 1966 March-October (Offsite-box 7, Folder 6-13)
    - Reading Files, 1968 January-June (Offsite-box 7, Folder 14-19)
    - Reading Files, 1968 July-December (Offsite-box 7, Folder 20-25)
    - Reading Files, 1969 January-May (Offsite-box 7, Folder 26-30)
  - Subseries I.E. Subject Files, 1958-1984 (bulk 1965-1973)
    Subseries I.E contains documentation related to various Model Cities subjects. Topics include activity in the New York City model neighborhoods (Central Brooklyn, South Bronx, and Harlem – East Harlem), housing development, policy development, and the Vest Pocket Housing program.
    Materials in this subseries are arranged alphabetically.
    - 100th Street, 1965 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 1)
    - 114th Street, 1965 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 2)
    - Abrams Report, 1966 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 3)
    - Administrative, 1968-1970 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 4)
    - Awards, 1967 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 5)
    - Board of Estimate, 1967-1969 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 6)
    - Bedford-Stuyvesant, 1966, 1968-1969 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 7-9)
    - Bronx (13 Folders), 1967-1970 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 10-22)
    - Brownsville (2 Folders), 1967-1973, bulk 1968-1969 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 23-24)
    - Budgets, 1967-1971 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 1)
    - Bushwick (1 of 2), 1968 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 2)
      1 item moved to an oversize container.
    - Bushwick (2 of 2). Oversize, 1968 (Folder OS-Large, Folder 2)
      File contains a zoning map for Bushwick. Proposed and recommended expansion sites are highlighted.
    - Central Brooklyn (10 Folders), 1964-1973, bulk 1968-1969 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 3-12)
    - Committee Meetings, 1968 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 13)
    - Community Groups, 1965-1967 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 14)
    - Community Participation, 1967-1968 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 15)
    - Computer Mapping, 1968 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence, 1968-1970 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 17)
    - Dealerships, 1969 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 18)
    - East New York (2 Folders), 1968-1976, bulk 1967-1970 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 19-20)
    - East New York (2 Folders), 1968-1976, bulk 1967-1970 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 1-2)
    - Economic Development, 1968-1969 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 3)
      This file contains a report on program approaches to economic development in Central Brooklyn.
    - Evaluation (3 Folders), 1969-1970 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 4-6)
      An evaluation of Model Cities progress in Central Brooklyn, South Bronx, and Harlem – East Harlem.
    - Executive Committee, Housing Subcommittee, 1962-1963 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 7)
    - Fulton Park Area, 1966 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 8)
    - General, 1967-1969 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 9)
    - Harlem - East Harlem (9 Folders), 1966-1970 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 10-18)
      Materials include Harlem Model Cities data from 1968, minutes of the Harlem – East Harlem Model Cities Policy Committee meetings, plans for a Harlem Jazz Center, and other documentation related to Model Cities activity in Harlem.
    - Harlem - East Harlem, 1966-1970 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 1)
    - History, 1966-1970 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 2)
    - Housing (6 Folders), 1958-1968 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 3-8)
    - Housing (2 Folders), 1971-1973 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 9-10)
      Contains several copies of "The Leflagi Plan for Housing Now"
    - Housing (2 Folders), 1966-1984, bulk 1967-1970 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 11-12)
    - Housing Executive Committee, 1966 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 13)
      Agendas and meeting minutes of the Housing Executive Committee
    - Housing Now, 1971-1973 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 14)
    - Housing Speeches, 1966 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 15)
    - HRA and Comm Corps (2 Folders), 1967-1969 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 16-17)